Guide to the Richard Poirier Collection,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Richard Poirier Collection,
1945-2007
[Bulk Dates: 1986-2007].
Poirier, Richard.
3.25 linear ft. (3 record storage cartons)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1572
8720686
Correspondence and writings of American professor, editor, and scholar of literature and popular culture, Richard Poirier.
Biographical Note
Richard Poirier, an American literary and cultural critic, professor of literature, and founder of Raritan: A Quarterly Review, was born September 9, 1925 in Gloucester Massachusetts. Poirier served in the Army during World War II, and upon returning from combat enrolled in Amherst College where he earned his B.A. He continued his studies in literature first at Yale where he earned his MA, and later at Harvard where he received a PhD in 1960.
Poirier taught at Harvard from 1958-1963, but he spent the majority academic career at Rutgers University where he was a prominent member and sometimes Chair of the English Department from 1963-2002.
Richard Poirier was not only a highly regarded scholar and teacher, but a well-respected editor and publisher as well. He co-founded the Library of America publishing venture in 1979. The Library of America is a non-profit publisher focused on publishing and preserving American poetry, fiction, and essays, often producing volumes of collected works that published pieces that would otherwise be out of print. He also co-founded Raritan: A Quarterly Review, out of what he perceived to be a dearth of serious criticism on American literature and culture that engaged both academics and non-academics.
Poirier regularly contributed essays and reviews to publications such as The Partisan Review (which he edited from 1963-1973), The New York Review of Books, and The London Review of Books. He authored a number of books, including works on Henry James, Robert Frost, and Ralph Waldo Emerson and collections of criticism such as The Perfoming Self: Compositions and Decompositions in the Languages of Contemporary Life.
Richard Poirier died in his Manhattan home on August 15, 2009.
Scope and Content
Papers contain material related to the personal and professional life of literary and cultural critic Richard Poirier. The bulk of the papers contain files related to Poirier's scholarly writing, but there is also correspondence related to his role as a professor, literary critic, and editor of the Raritan: A Quarterly Review.
The papers comprise only a small part of the Poirier collection; the majority of the collection contains books from Poirier's library, most annotated (some heavily) and many inscribed by their authors. The books reflect both Poirier's interest in the American literary tradition and his network of friends and admirers within the literary community.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 3 series
Series I: Correspondence, 1971-2007
Series II: Writings and Notes, Undated, 1986-1996
Series III: Biographical Material, 1945-1992
Subjects
Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1803-1882--Criticism and interpretation.; Frost, Robert, 1874-1963--Criticism and interpretation.; Hellman, Lillian, 1905-1984.; Poirier, Richard.; Vidal, Gore, 1925-; American literature--History and criticism.; Criticism--United States.; Scholarly periodicals.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Raritan.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Box 3, Folder 13 contains student papers and is restricted until 2056.
Acquisition
G. Thomas Tanselle Gift 05/05/2010 2009.2010.M112
- Series I: Correspondence, 1971-2007
  Series I is comprised of personal and professional correspondence received by Poirier, as well as some copies of his outgoing correspondence. The letters relate to his work as a literature professor at Rutgers, his role as editor of Raritan and personal correspondence between Poirier and his friends.
  - Alphabetical
    - A-Z, 1971-2007, (6 Folders) (Box 1)
    - Adams, Alice, 1992-1999 (Box 1)
    - Brommich, David, 1992-1998 (Box 1)
    - Burnshaw, Stanley, 1984-1999 (Box 1)
    - Donoghue, Denis, 1992-2000 (Box 1)
    - Ferry, David, 1992-2008 (Box 1)
    - Hellman, Lillian, 1978-1983 (Box 1)
    - Hollander, John, 1993-2004 (Box 1)
    - Hyman, Suzanne, 1998-2000 (Box 1)
    - Jehler, Myra, 1987-1993 (Box 1)
    - Kenmode, Frank, 1992-2007 (Box 1)
    - Merrell, James, 1992-2002 (Box 1)
    - Said, Edward, 1991-1999 (Box 1)
    - Seidel, Frederick and Mae Griswold (Box 1)
    - Vidal, Gore, 1974-1995, (2 Folders) (Box 1)
    - Weiseltier, Leon, 1987-1999 (Box 1)
  - Topical
    - Offers from Other Universities, 1978-1987 (Box 1)
    - Humanities 6 Course at Harvard (Box 1)
    - Harvard Advisory Committee, 1987-1991 (Box 1)
    - Lecture Invitations, 1990-1995 (Box 1)
    - Letters of Recommendation, 1990-2004 (Box 1)
    - Letters Received on the Publication of The Renewal of Literature, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Rutgers Univerity-- Amiri Baraka, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Reader's Catalogue, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Philip Poirier, 1979 (Box 1)
- Series II: Writings and Notes, Undated, 1986-1996
  The Writings and Notes Series includes research notes and manuscript drafts of many of Poirier's scholarly articles, books, and book reviews as well as some copies of published articles. These files are arranged topically by the subject of a work according to Poirier's own organizational and naming schemes. Therefore, researchers seeking material related to the book The Renewal of Literature, should look under "Emerson, Ralph Waldo" rather than the title of the book.
  This series also includes some lecture notes and teaching material, including student essays from a 1986 course Poirier taught at Rutgers. These student papers are restricted until 2056.
  - Unpublished or Uncollected Writings, undated, 1988-1996, (4 Folders) (Box 2)
  - Aesthetics of Radicalism (Box 2)
  - Balanchine, George (Box 2)
  - Bellow, Saul (Box 2)
  - Eliot, George (Box 2)
  - Eliot, T.S. (Box 2)
  - Emerson, Ralph Waldo, (5 Folders) (Box 2)
  - Frost, Robert, (6 Folders) (Box 2)
  - James, Henry (Box 2)
  - Joyce, James (Box 3)
  - London Review of Books, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Midler, Bette (Box 3)
  - O'Connor, Flannery (Box 3)
  - O'Hara, Frank (Box 3)
  - Pynchon, Thomas, (2 Folders) (Box 3)
  - Stein, Gertrude (Box 3)
  - Technology and Literary Technique (Box 3)
  - Vidal, Gore (Box 3)
  - Lecture Notes
    - General (Box 3)
    - Shakespeare (Box 3)
  - Student Papers, 1986 (Box 3)
    [Restricted until 2056]
  - Reviews of Poirier's Books, (2 Folders) (Box 3)
- Series III: Biographical Material, 1945-1992
  The Biographical Material series is comprised of a small amount of biographical material including, notably, some of Poirier's diaries from the 1970s and early 1980s.
  - CV and Resume (Box 3)
  - Diaries, 1973-1982 (Box 3)
  - Philip Poirier's Diaries, 1945 (Box 3)
  - Modern Language Association Panel on Poirier, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Salmagundi Interview with Poirier (Box 3)
  - Raritan Poirier tribute issue, 2010 (Box 3)